Hi, in this video we're going to take a
look at a couple of affordable FPGA
starter kits to get you into FPGAs. So
what I've got here is a couple of basic
entry-level FPGA kits. Three on the top
here are sub $100
boards that allow you to get up and
running. This is the uh
Papilio 1
uh Xilinx based FPGA board.
Similar sort of style to an Arduino
thing. You can connect wings on here and
stuff like that. You can even get an
Arduino compatible softcore processor to
program inside this thing. And this
thing's under 50 bucks and it's got a
you know a decent Xilinx FPGA on there.
Then we've got this Terasic
DE0 Nano board.
And this one is an Altera based board
and it's a nice little compact thing
like that. This one is $89
US. I think it's as little as $49 for US
students. So that one's quite reason-
quite reasonably priced. Then we've got
the Digilent Basis 2. It's an
sorry a Xilinx compatible like the
Papilio 1. It's got a Spartan 3E same as
what's on the Papilio there. And uh
yeah, it's a neat little unit. This one
only costs around $79 or $59 student
price. So not bad at all. It has a VGA
output as we'll take a look at. And then
we have a higher end one which is the
MicroZ
uh
board and it's Xilinx partner with
Avnet. And yes, this is the exclusive
Dave Jones edition. Beauty. If you're
going to get this, get the Dave Jones
edition one. Trust me. And this is
basically a Xilinx Uh, it's not one of
their Spartan ones one of their low-end
Spartans. It's one of their uh really
modern uh high-end zinc ones. And this
is an incredibly powerful board, $199
uh for this board, but it can run
embedded Linux. And you know, I think it
comes actually pre-programmed with
embedded Linux. And it's got Ethernet
and the whole works. So, quite a really
powerful beast and we'll take a a look
at that in more detail as well. So, take
a look at the uh Papilio board here.
Just an example of what's required
bare-bones to get this thing up and
running. Uh once again, this is a fairly
fine-pitch uh quad flat pack chip. So,
it's not something you can just
immediately mount on a breadboard, for
example. We need an external oscillator
to make the damn thing work. Then we
need our platform flash memory connected
to it so that uh it can store our
programs when we remove our power. Uh
we've got multiple voltage regulators up
here. 1.2 V, 2.5 V, 3.3 V. They're for
all the various core voltages required
by this particular Xilinx Spartan 3
FPGA. And then we've got the uh USB
interface here. I mean, you don't
necessarily need this. You could have
just had a JTAG header on there and just
plugged it straight in and then used an
external uh JTAG programmer for that.
But this one But all of these boards
have uh USB built in so you can just
connect them straight up to your PC. And
that's what you want. And if you do want
to program these things yourself, which
yeah, it's a great thing to do. I highly
recommend it. Just watch out for all the
traps for young players. You can get um
the external uh programmers. In this
case, JTAG programmer. Xilinx uh do this
one, the Platform USB cable. This one's
uh fairly uh cheap on eBay, not as cheap
as the Altera ones. This is not a
genuine one. This is actually a uh
rip-off one. And so is this Altera uh
USB uh blaster one. You can get these
for like I think this one is like
something crazy like $8 delivered
something ridiculous like that. So,
Altera
does seem to have a lower entry point
price as far as the
JTAG programmer tool goes. That it
supports that is supported by the
official
manufacturer software. Now, the two
major players in the market, well, in
fact, all the FPGA players in the
market, but the two main ones are Xilinx
and Altera. They all offer free tools
and as you can see on this basis, too,
it's advertised that you can use the
free CAD tools from Xilinx. In this
case, the ISE WebPACK. It's a massive
download, of course, but it is
completely free and Xilinx have the and
sorry, Altera have their version as well
for free. But, the free versions of the
tools don't necessarily support the
higher-end FPGAs. So, that's why if
you're going to get one of these boards,
you have to ensure that it is suitable
for use of what whatever FPGA you
choose, you have to en- sure that it's
compatible with the free tools.
Otherwise, you'll be paying a fortune
for the FPGA tools. Now, this Papilio 1
is an open-source hardware type
platform, but it is very basic. It's so
I don't think it's going to be as sort
of, you know, hand-holding as some more
of the
sort of kits from more of the mainstream
providers. Brief look at the DE0-Nano
here. I rather like this really compact
little form factor. Nice 0.1 in headers
on here and well, that's actually
there's some stuff on the bottom, memory
and bypass and things like that. And
also another header on the bottom to
plug it into stuff. Mounted on
standoffs. Neat little self-contained
unit. And as I said, it's got a
Altera Cyclone IV FPGA. It's got a USB
interface. It's got an E-squared PROM.
It's got What have we got? Four DIP
switches. It's got an accelerometer
built on. Fantastic if you're into
accelerometer stuff. It's got an ADC in
there.
What else have we got? We've got two
push buttons, 40-pin GPIO headers, 32
megabits of SD RAM. Fairly chunky amount
of SD RAM in there.
And it's got a serial PROM to program
the well, to hold the configuration
program and eight LEDs. So, not a bad
little board. I don't mind that at all.
The other really good thing about the
DE0 Nano, it comes with the software.
So, you don't have to download it. And
most importantly, the Altera complete
design suite, the free package. Cuz this
is absolutely huge. As you can see, it's
on a DVD. It can be multi-gigabytes to
download the various packages from the
manufacturers. This one supplies it for
you. The others don't. And the Basis 2
board, it's much larger than the DE0
Nano. There's a comparison there.
0.1-in female headers along here. So,
not as many IO as you get on the DE0
Nano, but you do get more nice big
chunky switches and buttons. We've got a
four-way LED display here. You can have
it as a clock. What I really like is
that it's got a VGA output. And that's
really quite nice. Cuz one of the best
examples for an FPGA is being able to
interface to a VGA monitor. Cuz you can
pick up VGA monitors from the garbage
room for nothing, right? People throw
these out. They make great interfaces
for FPGA projects. So, this one allows
you to experiment off the bat with that.
So, that's really quite good at the
expense of some IO along here. But yeah,
once again, it's got the platform flash
memory, multiple clock sources once
again.
Xilinx Spartan 3E this time instead of
the Altera part. And it's got a PS2 port
on it as well. And you can get modules
that actually plug into this. This was
I'm not sure of what type or how much
they are, but anyway, you can plug those
suckers in, but I really like this one
because it's got a VGA output you can
experiment with and presumably some
example programs to drive the VGA. This
much more upmarket MicroZ board is a
$199 one. Um, unfortunately, it doesn't
really come with any IO, like usable IO.
Of course, it's designed to have, you
know, embedded Linux. It uses the
high-end Zynq FPGA. Really neat. It's
got a built-in ARM 9 processor. Really
powerful thing. Runs embedded Linux. I
think it's already pre-programmed with
it out of the box. We have to power it
up and have a look. Ethernet interface,
of course, but all of the IO here is on
the bottom. It's got an SD microSD card
on the bottom. All the IO here is
designed to plug into a rather expensive
IO board, which I don't have. Wasn't
provided with this thing, which is being
a bit of a bummer. It's a really big
board, which I'll post a photo of right
now. That just breaks out all of the IO
into handy
usable stuff. So, if you're going to get
one of these, I'd recommend you spring
the extra and get that IO board. I stand
corrected. This sucker contains two, not
one, but two 1-gig
1-GHz, folks, ARM Cortex-A9
hard processor cores in there as well,
of course, as all the FPGA fabric as
well. It's got two 1-meg sample AD
converters as well. So, really powerful
board, that one. So, if you're looking
to run something inside a traditional as
it like inside a traditional processor,
you know, these hardcore ones are better
than, you know, the soft cores you can
program into any almost any FPGA as long
as it's got enough enough gates inside,
enough room in there. You can program
Um, uh, different types of softcore
processors into these things, but you
know, something like this dedicated, um,
9 1 GHz processor in there cannot be
beat. Uh, really, it just absolutely
kills any softcore processor that you
can, uh, program into any other FPGA
fabric. And also, you don't want to piss
away your FPGA fabric inside these
things with the softcore processor. Like
you might put a softcore processor in
here, but it might use, I don't know,
um, just as a guess, you know, it might
use that 10 or 20% of your FPGA space
depending on, uh, what type of processor
it is.
Don't want to waste it. And they're
usually not going to be very quick. Like
the FPGA itself, uh, for example, might
be very, very quick, but when you, uh,
compile in, not the correct term, but
we'll use that today, um, an FPGA,
uh, core, softcore into this thing, it
can't run, you know, at nearly that
speed. You can get them to run at tens
of MHz, 50 MHz, maybe.
So, this certainly won't be a, uh,
complete tutorial in, uh, how to, you
know, set up and run these things. I'll,
uh, basically won't uh, show you
anything. I'm just going to, uh, install
it and get them running. And that's the
whole idea. How easy is it to get these
things running? I'll just tell you in
the end. I won't show you all the
horrible steps to it. So, we'll start
out with the DE0 Nano and, uh, that of
course has the Altera, um, Cyclone part
on it. So, we're going to install the,
uh, thankfully, the, uh, software comes
on that, uh, DVD. We didn't have to
download it, however big it is, however
many gigabytes. We're just going to
install that. So, here we go. Install
free package and
well, see what pops out the other end.
When you install it, uh, you have the
option to install that Quartus II. You
have to install that. It's the with free
web edition. It is the actual suite of
tools for all the FPGA stuff. So,
there's no getting around that, but you
can also install the ModelSim, uh, as
well. And that's just, uh, simulation
stuff. And most beginners probably don't
need ModelSim. So, if you want to save
the 2.7 gig, you certainly can. And that
only took 23 minutes. That wasn't too
bad, I guess. Can be a lot worse than
that, trust me. And well, no, I don't
wish you to talk back enable sending
talk back. No, go away. Anyway, um it's
finished and it installed, as you can
see well, it installed all the different
families down here, not just the uh
Cyclone 4, I think, which we needed.
Installed, you know, Stratix, real
high-end stuff, Area, and all those.
What the FPGA is this garbage? The
software install has now started
thrashing the CD drive and locked up.
This was after it said it installed and
everything was hunky-dory. And this just
goes on and on and on forever. You got
to be me.
Ah.
And on the other CD that comes with it,
uh there's no install file or anything
like that. There's just uh some
subdirectories with all the stuff.
There's uh various uh demonstration
programs. Oh, look, my first FPGA. That
sounds neat. There's all the uh uh files
for the um Altera Quartus uh stuff, the
ADC stuff, and yeah, uh there's the uh
accelerometer, by the looks of it. So,
that one looks uh quite neat. And then
we've got uh the data sheets with the um
uh all of the various uh parts. That's
pretty handy. And uh we got the
schematic. Fantastic. And we can load
that up. And bingo, there it is. And we
can have a look at uh how they've
implemented this thing.
There we go. Not sure what package
they've used to uh use that. It's not
Altium. But uh yeah, once again, they've
done all the separate pages. This is
very common for these FPGA vendors. It
It's sometimes it's good, sometimes it's
not so great. That's how they've
implemented the uh configuration prom
and the JTAG interface, and everything's
just spread over a couple of pages here.
So, that is a little bit annoying, but
uh
But there you go. They give you all the
complete schematics, which you will need
to um interface this thing. And you
notice here's all the uh power supplies,
3.3 V, 2.5 V, 1.2 V for the various
cores on the FPGAs cuz these FPGAs can
be a real pain in the ass. Now,
according to the quick start guide, we
can just run one of the demonstration
programs here, a batch file in here
after installing our uh Quartus II
software, which we've done, and uh
and Bob's your uncle, it should download
and everything's right because these
FPGA tools are actually command line
tools. You don't have to use the GUIs.
Um and in fact, you know, that's how a
lot of uh third-party tools integrate
with these FPGA tools is they're all
command line driven. So, let's go in
there and try it. Uh G sensor, here it
is, demo.bat.
And cuz there's no batch file in there,
so we should
have to just run test.bat, I guess.
Let's see if it works. Does it work?
Demo. No.
What? There was some red thing there, I
saw it. Oh,
fail. And that error message was that it
hadn't detected my uh USB Blaster
because this board actually has that USB
Blaster uh functionality compatibility
uh built in to the board as I showed
before you could buy for like $8 that
external programmer. It's built in, but
look, it um yeah, it just didn't install
properly. Oh,
it's supposed to do that when you
install the Altera Quartus software.
You've got to be kidding me. All right,
I manually installed the drivers.
They're in the usual uh location in the
Quartus software under
/drivers/quartus/drivers/usbblaster
and did the usual Windows thing. So, one
more time for the dummies, here we go,
test.bat.
Woohoo!
Look.
It's doing it.
It's doing it. It's doing the business.
Well, it's doing something.
Uh my LEDs are still uh flashing. By the
way, that um uh LED um
you know, Knight Rider type thing, wait,
um came uh pre-installed with the board,
which is really quite nice. Oh, there we
go. Looks like it's done. It worked a
treat. Beautiful. I don't even get over
that driver issue. Not a problem. Thumbs
up. And yeah, check it out. We are in a
command line interface. Man, look I can
go CLS and it actually clears the
screen. Hello. Command not found. Now,
this uh, certainly won't be a tutorial
on how to use Altera Quartus II, that's
for sure. I just wanted to show that we
can actually load our project into that.
And all I did was double click on the
project file within that uh, demo
subdirectory, that accelerometer sensor
we just ran and bingo, here it is loaded
into Quartus II and there's our source
code. Fantastic. And if you want to do,
of course, we can just modify our demo
program, then we can go over here and
actually uh, compile the thing. We can
analyze, synthesize, fit and then
program the device down there. So, we
can just double click on analysis. Do
you want to run the task again? Yep,
here we go. It's going to go through
analysis and synthesis and yeah, it was
successful. There's six warnings, not a
problem. So, it all just works. Total
logic elements, there we go. Used only
only used 189 logic elements. Total uh,
dedicated logic registers, total
registers 112, not much at all. And then
we can do the same thing for the place
and route. Here we go. I'm uh, it's
almost complete there and should
successful. Four warning error messages.
Total logic elements used, look, less
than 1% of what that FPGA is capable of.
Total pins, all that sort of jazz.
Beautiful. Total memory bits and total
PLLs used. It's using one PLL. Uh,
there's four uh, phase lock loops within
this FPGA. And uh, there you go. That's
a handy little summary. And there's a
million different uh, things and
resources we can check and things like
that. One neat one is the resource
utilization by entity here. You just go
into analysis and synthesis and it can
give you all this
sort of info. But, this basically tells
us that how many logic elements in our
FPGA are being used by each particular
Verilog routine there within our program
over here. So, that's rather neat. Let's
try a more media project. I've opened up
that Nios embedded core
demo program, and I've done the analysis
and place and route on that, and it
didn't take that long, and look, here it
is. Summary of that after place and
route. I've only used 26% of our
you know, cheap ass FPGA to run that
soft core. It's running external DRAM
and everything else. So, that's not as
pretty good, you know, on a low-end
cheap ass board like this. I like it.
Now, there's a million and one neat
different things we can do with all the
tools built into this thing, but one I
really like is the power analyzer. Now,
after we run the assembler down here,
then we can go up into our tools, and
sorry, there's a whole bunch of tools.
There's million and one tools you can
do. Logic analyzers, signal tapping. Oh.
Good stuff. Anyway,
let's go to the power play power
analyzer tool. And we can run that. I've
already run that, and we can go to the
report here. Hello, McFly.
Come on. Go into the report. There it
is. It simulates the whole thing. Tells
us how much power that program is going
to be running. Here is total thermal
power dissipation 282 mW to run that
Nios soft core processor there. So, you
know, that's pretty neat. And here's a
summary of the results. 350 mW total
thermal power dissipation for that Nios
core there, but we can go in and we can
get all sorts of things. Total power
dissipation by block types. We can get
power dissipation by hierarchy here.
Come on. This is slow as a wet week.
Man, I'm only running a 2 GHz core i7
here. I'm not sure what's going on.
Maybe it's my screen capture in the
background, but all these breakdowns of
all the power dissipation. Fantastic
stuff.
And you can even get an estimate of what
current is going to be drawn here from
each of the uh individual power rails.
The like the IO, that was based on a I
think it was a 12 and 1/2% uh toggle
rate or something like that. So, it's
just an estimation, but if you see AVCC
D, the internal power dissipation, the
static current, fantastic. And of
course, one thing you're definitely
going to want to well, you're forced
into um
when you're doing FPGAs, one of the big
things is of course assigning pins cuz
the pins can do many different
functions. So, uh Altera Quartus II has
the pin planner here. And um this one's
obviously already loaded up for this
particular project and this particular
device here, the EP4C blah blah blah.
And you can see the for the BGA part,
all of these ridiculous um symbols for
the pin outs. But you can go in there
and you can form groups, the DRAM, where
the DRAM's connected to and the GPIOs
and the keys and the LEDs and the
switches. All for And you can create
your own new groups and things like
that, which then you can assign into
your
uh into your Verilog VHDL program to uh
you know,
to access your IO and things like that.
So, here's all our pins, all of our
individual pins, and we can set the IO
standard here. We can change all that
and we can do all sorts of weird and
wonderful and wacky stuff with our pin
IO, but that's
man, there's just IO configuration in
FPGAs is a 2-hour tutorial in its own
right. And there's countless other stuff
as well in this in both the Altera and
the Xilinx tools and the tools from
other lesser manufacturers as well. And
yeah, I could do a million videos on
these and still not cover them. As you
can see, these are very very complex
tools, these FPGAs. And you know, pretty
much if you're doing it at this sort of
level using these vendor tools as
they're called, then you know, you have
to learn how to do these things. But, uh
by loading in these example projects and
getting everything up and running, then
it takes, you know, and then working
backwards from that, that takes all at
least the uh you know, the the Hello
World grief out of it cuz FPGAs are
incredibly difficult and complex just to
get, you know, the blinky LED going,
really. But, I haven't touched on one of
the awesome things that comes with this
DEO Nano. If you want to create a new
project from scratch, how do you do it?
Well, with the uh disk here comes some
tools and they've got a control panel
that allows you to control stuff, but
there's system builder stuff. Let's give
this a go.
Here it is. Look at this. Teras-
Terasic? Don't know how to pronounce
that bloody name. It's a bit hard, but
here's the DEO Nano FPGA board and you
can
EV blog, let's call our project here.
And what do you want to use? I want to
use a clock, I want to use a couple of
buttons, I want to use SRAM, I want to
use everything. And what Oh, look, 5
megapixel camera. Looks like they've got
some modules that you can whack on to
the header. That's pretty neat. 4 and a
half uh 4.3-in LCD and touch multi-touch
LCDs. Presumably, you can just buy
those, plug them in. Anyway, um the
whole idea is this will generate a code
template for you that you can work from
and take all that really annoying pin
configuration stuff and things like that
out of the equation. So, here we go.
Let's try it. I haven't tried it yet,
but let's generate GPIO header.
There we go. Well, you know, we've got
none. Let's just go GPIO default, shall
we? And let's just go generate.
And it will generate uh Here we go. I'll
save it and then we'll try and do
something. And here it is. Code
generated. EV blog and bingo, there's
our code. Let's check it out. We can
load that. Just load up the uh Quartus
project file here
and
we're in like Flynn. And here is our
project all with our template already
set up. Here's our DRAM configuration,
the LEDs, key switches, everything is
set up
ready to go. Then we can just add our
own code on top of that. Beautiful. And
then we've got this bit of a wanky
control panel software that comes with
it, but it just allows you to have a
basic play. It just talks to the board
and then just allows you to
you know switch the LEDs off and on and
you know touch the switches and things
like that and you know
write stuff to the memory and play with
the accelerometer.
There it is. We can muck around and
ADC bugger off a vast go away. And then
you know and then we can just you know
play around with it but really you know
that's not a huge value add that's just
more of a toy but that system builder
stuff that is a real Bobby dazzler let
me tell you that is essential for
beginners to build to generate those
code templates to get you up and running
cuz nothing is worse than your FPGA that
just you know that just does nothing. As
a beginner you just you know try to get
and configure all your pins and just get
all the assignments and everything
working just so the damn thing compiles
and that can be a real hurdle whereas
that code generator huge step.